Register of the Giles Udy Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Giles Udy collection
circa 2004-2011
2011C62
Udy, Giles, collector
483 digital files (135 MB)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Photographs of the sites of forced labor camps near Noril'sk, Russia.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2011.
Location of Original Materials
The original photographs in their native file format remain with Giles Udy.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Giles Udy is an independent academic and a member of the Council of the Keston Institute, formerly Keston College. His long-term work is on the history of the gulag camps of Norilsk, but he has also published research on the impact of Soviet Communism in British politics between the wars.
See also: Giles Udy website, copyright 2008 by Giles Udy, http://www.gilesudy.com/
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection of born-digital, chiefly color photographs of Noril'sk is accompanied by Udy's notes, which describe the geography, history, and function of the subjects depicted. The images are of landscapes and buildings; virtually no people are shown.
Three types of files are in the collection: PDF files containing photographs by Udy, JPG files that appear to be chiefly historical photographs acquired by Udy, and DOC files containing Udy's descriptions of the general subject content of the photographs. The files available to researchers are the only versions available at Hoover; no higher quality files were received by Hoover.
To protect his copyright, Udy provided most of the photographs to Hoover in PDF format with an embedded copyright statement.
The dates of the collection are based on the "date modified" field of the few JPG files provided to Hoover.
The directory structure, folder names and file names were retained by Hoover almost exactly as received from Giles Udy. The directory structure consists of folders with descriptive names; it is the basis of the container list. Many of the file names are also descriptive, though many others follow this alphanumeric form: DSCN1234.pdf. Because the descriptive folder and file names were very long, occasionally exceeding the file system limit of some operating systems, and contained many characters not recommended for file names, Hoover staff slightly altered some file names while retaining their descriptive nature. The creator's full file names were documented and can be provided on request.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in a single series, Photographs of Noril'sk.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Forced labor--Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--Pictorial works.
Collection Contents
- Photographs of Noril'sk, circa 2004-2011; 483 digital files (Reading room workstation)
  Arranged by location or subject, and accompanied by notes written by Udy
  - Photographs of camps and settlements west of Noril'sk, circa 2004-2011; 132 digital files
    - Alevrolitnyĭ mining camp/penal camp
    - Zapadnyĭ settlement
    - Kayerkan settlement
    - Kalargon penal camp cell block
  - Photographs of Lake Lama camp, circa 2004-2011; 59 digital files; This was a pine syrup extraction camp 100 kilometers east of Noril'sk
    - Baltic officers memorials on shore of Lake Lama
    - Former NKVD rest house nearby
    - Miscellaneous views, Provided as background interest
  - Photographs of Medvezhiĭ Rucheĭ settlement, circa 2004-2011; 31 digital files
    - Medvezhiĭ Rucheĭ settlement
    - Nickel mining sites and buildings
    - Tundra looking south from nickel mine dumps
  - Photographs of Mt. Schmidt, circa 2004-2011; 39 digital files
    Includes old city, new city and mines
  - Photographs of Noril'sk old city, circa 2004-2011; 49 digital files; The old city dates from the mid-1930s to early 1950s
    - Residential and administrative buildings
    - Industrial sites
    - Prison, The prison dates to before 1950
  - Photographs of Noril'sk old city memorial area by old camp graveyard, circa 2004-2011; 80 digital files
    - General site views
    - Polish memorial
    - Baltic memorials
    - Russian memorials
    - New Jewish memorial, This dates to 2005
    - New memorial, This dates to 2005-2006
  - Photographs of Noril'sk - Dolgoe Ozero (Long Lake) and causeway between old and new cities, circa 2004-2011; 11 digital files
  - Photographs of Noril'sk new city, circa 2004-2011; 75 digital files; This was designated as a city in 1956 but began earlier. The early buildings were built chiefly by prisoners
    - Entrance to new city from causeway across lake
    - City center
    - Gulag-era buildings
    - Camp 5-6 administration building
    - Miscellaneous sites of interest
  - Photographs of Noril'sk from outside the city, circa 2004-2011; 3 digital files
  - Sample Google Earth screenshots of Noril'sk industrial archaeology, circa 2004-2011; 4 digital files; Provided to indicate what can be done to identify the original sites of the Norillag/Gorlag camp complex from memoirs, original maps and drawings, combined with on-site and satellite investigation